<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2019-12-30T21:21:43+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Chromicle</title><subtitle>blog and more
</subtitle><author><name>Ajay prabhakar</name><email>ajayprabhakar369@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">First post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018-12-16-First-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First post" /><published>2018-12-16T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-12-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/First-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018-12-16-First-post/">&lt;p&gt;Catching up with the apps, more appropriately the networking apps has become quite a challenge lately. While some recent ones are getting very popular, older ones are also holding their ground. Interestingly enough older ones are becoming mature as well whether or not they want to be. They are now getting called at the principal’s office and stuff. Seems like they’re now being treated like teenage crossed human beings who are anticipated to be more responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, back to the point for today — &lt;strong&gt;Complexity of Usage&lt;/strong&gt;. I don’t know about others, it takes quite some effort for me to gain the basic understanding of the latest apps. Let me give some example. Several months ago I was trying to figure out how to add a story in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instagram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I was going all over the icons and options and it was a thorny way to be honest. After 8-10 minutes of uttermost struggle, I was finally able to figure it out. And it was indeed an &lt;strong&gt;Aha&lt;/strong&gt; moment. Maybe that’s how the senior citizens feel when they figure out some &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Facebook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; stuff and now I know the feelings. With some sheer confidence by my side after cracking such complicated puzzle, I headed straight to the play store and installed &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Snapchat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; without any hesitation in mind. Only if I knew what was waiting ahead. The whole thing was complicated, the whole damn thing. Nothing was making any sense to me. I was ratted and completely demolished. But being a true supporter of Bangladesh National Cricket team, I didn’t lose hope. The optimistic part somewhere inside kept me from uninstalling it in hope that someday I’ll come again and conquer. I’m really happy to announce that &lt;strong&gt;someday&lt;/strong&gt; came true last week. It was an absolute &lt;strong&gt;Eureka&lt;/strong&gt; moment rest assured. I wouldn’t say everything makes complete sense now but I have the basic drills of doing stuffs. I’m in an &lt;strong&gt;okay-but-why&lt;/strong&gt; state now and in the process of convincing myself that’s the way it should be.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ajay prabhakar</name><email>ajayprabhakar369@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Catching up with the apps, more appropriately the networking apps has become quite a challenge lately. While some recent ones are getting very popular, older ones are also holding their ground. Interestingly enough older ones are becoming mature as well whether or not they want to be. They are now getting called at the principal’s office and stuff. Seems like they’re now being treated like teenage crossed human beings who are anticipated to be more responsible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Example post 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018-12-09-week-49/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Example post 1" /><published>2018-12-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-12-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/week-49</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018-12-09-week-49/">&lt;p&gt;I don’t have much in mind this week. Which means the hash value is going to be rather smaller. Meaning I need some extra padding with it for keeping the size consistent. I’ve always believed that I’m very bad in this business. Keeping it concise is my thing. At least my subconscious mind loves to think so. But wait, has it been always like this? After careful consideration I have figured out at least one aspect of my life where I was rather elaborate. It is none other than the exam papers up until I started my undergrad. “The customer is always right” and it’s even more prominent when the consumer is going to mark you. And also if the pen is mightier than the sword then the mark point must also be tougher than the gun point, right? That’s why we’re maybe even more concerned than the writers about the significance of the namings of their literatures. We’re more thoughtful about what they tried to mean with some specific lines and explain them in a way maybe they never even thought of. I’ve always wondered about the way they’d react if they could come to see our bisection of their writings. Would they be able to keep up with our level of expectation if they’d know what we think? Or would they go like, “We haven’t thought that far when writing, please believe!”? I guess we’ll never know the answer and on our defense, we were on mark point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life took another minor version bump after figuring out the fact that it is possible to set the timer to :90(90 seconds) instead of 1:30(1 minute and 30 seconds) in microwave oven(at least it’s true for the one I use) and that’s what I actually wanted to say this week.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ajay prabhakar</name><email>ajayprabhakar369@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I don’t have much in mind this week. Which means the hash value is going to be rather smaller. Meaning I need some extra padding with it for keeping the size consistent. I’ve always believed that I’m very bad in this business. Keeping it concise is my thing. At least my subconscious mind loves to think so. But wait, has it been always like this? After careful consideration I have figured out at least one aspect of my life where I was rather elaborate. It is none other than the exam papers up until I started my undergrad. “The customer is always right” and it’s even more prominent when the consumer is going to mark you. And also if the pen is mightier than the sword then the mark point must also be tougher than the gun point, right? That’s why we’re maybe even more concerned than the writers about the significance of the namings of their literatures. We’re more thoughtful about what they tried to mean with some specific lines and explain them in a way maybe they never even thought of. I’ve always wondered about the way they’d react if they could come to see our bisection of their writings. Would they be able to keep up with our level of expectation if they’d know what we think? Or would they go like, “We haven’t thought that far when writing, please believe!”? I guess we’ll never know the answer and on our defense, we were on mark point.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Example post 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018-12-02-week-48/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Example post 2" /><published>2018-12-02T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-12-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/week-48</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018-12-02-week-48/">&lt;p&gt;Just came to understand lately that all lands are eventually islands. It is only the enclaves who are treated differently. My life will never be the same again. Natural minority I should say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rabindranath Tagore died in 1941. India, Sri Lanka and Bangladesh got independence respectively in 1947, 1948 and 1971. India’s and Bangladesh’s national anthems are written by Rabindranath Tagore while Sri Lanka’s national anthem is inspired by his work. So basically he’s written national anthems for the nations that were yet to be born without even knowing their names. What a visionary and what an absolute spoiler. I wonder if he put any “Spoiler Alert” tag before his compositions. Otherwise the British Empire mustn’t be very happy about it considering the amount of anger people convey these days when they get spoiler for just a movie or a TV show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the new YouTube Music app is on the market and the monthly subscription fee for the premium version costs more than the monthly subscription fee of Netflix or Amazon Prime. Is the music just gonna play on the mobile or the singers gonna come home for some live action as well? What am I missing here? YouTube Music and chill is on it’s way maybe!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ajay prabhakar</name><email>ajayprabhakar369@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Just came to understand lately that all lands are eventually islands. It is only the enclaves who are treated differently. My life will never be the same again. Natural minority I should say.</summary></entry></feed>